sit so I want to talk about brahma
vihara again hmm and if you have things
sir we've been discussing how the brahma
vihara practice is the practice of the
peaceful life the life of non-conflict
hmm
so to say just say me get something to
say so my idea is that these four
aspects of brahma vihara was a one mind
meta Karuna mudita who Pecola
these four aspects need to be discerned
one by one mm-hmm and when a when Metis
descent and main steady one can
understand Karuna hmm one can then
discern who dieter and then one can then
decide Rebecca
then it's fulfilled that peaceful minded
peaceful life is being lived so more
regularly than instead of saying one by
one it's one within the other it's just
the development of that peaceful mind so
by understanding what man tells you
understand the principle ground all for
grammar viharas then within that
understanding of meta development of
matter you can develop Karuna within
development of melting Karuna didn't get
to develop mudita which then results in
development of baker you don't abandon
maintain order to develop Karuna you
don't abandon math and coruña in order
to the mudita
new to abandon meta Colonel Baker Baker
encompasses them all but in order to
arrive at it you have to follow through
them so to speak so it's not like or I
do meta I feel accomplished now find out
what Corona is I feel accomplished if
you keep doing meta you will arrive at
Rebecca basically same if you keep
following the principle of the first
jhana you will arrive at the fourth but
so the idea is peacefulness non-conflict
hmm on that general level level of it
will be referred to as a framework not
an individual level of the content of
your experience so at the in terms of
meta the Buddha seemed to mean non your
will rather than an active friendly
activity yeah of course of course
so it's not
no new framework of normal will the mind
of non yield will means even on when on
a particular level in terms of the
content of your car in sight sound smell
taste touch
there is something disagreeable you will
not have your will towards it because
you prioritize protecting the mind of
non you will regardless of what content
that mind is experiencing so in terms of
whenever you experience something
unpleasant you have non ill-will towards
it Jeff non-business yes to it yeah yeah
exactly Nonya will means non resist which is
Nonya will means non resist which is
which is different from a Thomas them
what I usually read as a practice for
meta is you sort of you have metaphor
things you like right regenerate love
yeah and that feeling of love you have
pleasure towards something you like what
else what you keep going
well that's not what it does look mean
yeah so it's usually the contemporary
notions of what spirituality and
everything else because it's a it's more
palpable it's more palpable for people
to serve and it's it's nice it's better
to to think in the in that kind of
loving-kindness manner towards people
then to dislike them or ignore them but
it's a mistake to regard that as a
practice of the Dhamma that's the
problem here like really if you want to
think positive thoughts about everyone
by all means but don't mistake that for
the practice of Dharma because if you do
then you won't look for what the actual
Dharma and meta is in the suttas and
that's the main problem not like saying
that that's not Dhamma doesn't mean you
should not do it because it's a nice
it's certainly a good way to relate with
people because not hating them means
they will not hate you back more often
they're not so it's just gonna help you
in that the level of society because
even people make that into spiritual
practice that's when they're going wrong
but without understanding what the
Buddha meant exact so you end up just
practicing Dhamma
rooted in like how you feel as you know
this makes me feel good does that's the
practice of the Dhamma and that's more
often than not wrong
because your feelings that will be
affected by your own resistance towards
it or indulgence the world it so if
that's the only criteria for following
what the practice of Dharma it means
your just your criteria of what Dhamma
is your routine of ignorance criteria of
craving so matter in me what the Buddha
means is non ill-will yeah framework of
no never mind of no no no so if it was
love see but it's also it's not this is
why I keep saying it's the mind of non
yoga not just known your will because I
might not have your will toward you but
I have your will towards him that
doesn't mean I'm doing method toward you
because I don't hate you either way
basically my mind is not developed in
regard to Metta even if I don't hate
anybody individually that still doesn't
mean you're developing Metta in order to
the other met you need to recognize that
framework that absence of your will as
the basis for your mind state that you
then choose to protect and maintain
regardless of who comes basically in
your field and field of vision under
circumstance regardless of the signals
and regardless of the elements
regardless of anything you you're
subjected to you you because you always
have a choice so I can now ignore the
mind of non you well as a priority and I
can choose to prioritize what I'm
experiencing right in front of you as in
dealing with you dealing with that
dealing with this upset dealing with
that pleasure whatever and that choice
basically means you abandon the
framework for the sake of the content
that's within that framework and that's
why you're not developing metal okay
that's why that suta which is again
contemporarily completely misread and
miss chanted I remember that and it's
all due to like putting a different
punctuation you know the line we spoke
about it before she liked the famous
line they were he purred like a mother
protects a child like that line refers
to the he protects his mind of no neol
will like a mother protects her only
child and then you think I must regard
everybody like my own children that's
completely not what it means but it
means that if you regard your own mind
as your only child as it
so important and precious to not to lose
sight of it mind of non your will you
will automatically cherish all living
beings and if you don't don't need to
take my word for it you could just like
see which one then encompasses which
principle either the one I described or
the principle of cherishing all living
beings you like your children which one
better corresponds to all four Brahma
viharas which one better corresponds to
all other aspects of the Dharma
teachings whereby when the mother
brought the baby and left it in front of
the other hand he didn't even look at it
and then in the end and the wife
realized this he will leave this child
to die that's how much he does not care
about it and the ship came back picked
up the child and left and the people
reported that to the Buddha and he said
well done that's how every element and
monk should act so which one of all of
those instances would be then
encompassed which principle Buddha
composit better the one I'm describing
whereby if you protect your mind as your
only child
you automatically cannot love nor hate
you can automatic a not hate no love or
being federated or emotionally bound
with the whole world and that's far
better than loving and being emotionally
bonded or the principle of loving
everyone how do you then tie them in
with being indifferent to everyone so
but indifference comes as a result of
excessive love that's not how it works
and you already know that even without
an insight into Thomas's that love
breeds well love breeds Equalization
yeah and then makes you makes us
susceptible to a version makes you
acceptable to fear and anxiety over what
you love because now you must but you
have no say in it yet you dependent on
it emotional and existential someone
would come up and my just drama to
destroy the thing that you love exactly
and that's what is against like what is
the Buddha described to fit that he was
sensuality he said it's like for the
sake of enjoying the ripe mangoes you
find the tree and somebody else who also
wants to enjoy those mangoes cannot
climb the tree but they can cut it and
unless you come down and abandon you
enjoying and eating and protecting and
being infatuated with your fruit you
will suffer on account of that tree
being cut and probably even die
so that for the minute by all means have
positive thoughts there was the whole
world but do not mistake that to be the
matter that they will describe they
would result in Becca and utter complete
freedom from the slightest conceit and
everything else and an attachment to the
world if you can't see the connection
between meta and you can't see that yeah
that means your meta needs are either
very defined and so the the further
development is then Karuna getting it
most human steadier which is non cruelty
so which is the game to me it sounds
similar to not in a non craving in a way
you know non trading is the ultimate non
cozy well yeah it's basically taking the same
well yeah it's basically taking the same
principle a step further now yeah so
first you have obvious like you meet
disagreeable you have your will towards
it
my novel well you develop the mind of
non your will in regard to disagreeable
but then you have that kind of still a
degree of some resistance if you were to
develop the mind of of that non you will
you will be then cultivating the non
resistance it then becomes like Karuna
the next step as in you refine the same
principle of non resistance because
that's part of what's in common to to to
make a coruña mudita newpaper resistant
non resistance means no craving non
conflict conflict mean yeah but that
it's all it's got to do with
understanding wisdom discernment you
know for example at the time apart verse
3 it says you recognize nobody wants to
get hurt yeah you don't want to get yet
so why so it's a rhetoric that
understanding is compassionate oh that's
why me if understanding is correct you
don't have to do the compassion the
result is compassion
so that stating of the discernment of
exactly yeah not emulating the
compassion by visualizing friendliness
and love side examine yeah yeah or daddy
can you like to saving other people's
lives and so on if you can help without
whatever any cost of your own well-being
that's great even if you want to
sacrifice yourself that's fine I'm sure
you have your reasons but in terms of
the Dhamma practice
none of that would be the practice of
the Dhamma right so dummies development
of the mind it's a in regard to whatever
is felt Pleasant unpleasant give is
unpleasant you don't there's no
resistance there exactly
and there isn't you're not trying to get
it you're not child yeah just change
circumstances Jackie the reason what
people would want to get the things that
a pleasant is because there is also
degree of resistance to the lack of that
pleasure it's not pleasant enough in you
resist that you don't know you don't
want to accept that you want to change
it so regardless of see if you develop
family harness you will be overcoming
centrality as well because its
sensuality is also formal resistance
just instead of resisting against the
content of your experience you are
resisting towards more of it because it
you can the practice of it so that
peaceful mind in regards to whatever is
felt that's the really good practice you
practice drawing artists in regard to
how you cut it
whatever common feeling is presently
enduring you are already practicing that
framework inadvertently you don't even
think about the framework in the more
general picture the non content just
have non resistance in regard to present
enduring feeling that's it non
resistance towards more of it non
resistance away from it non resistance
towards ignoring you couldn't possibly
try to hurt someone because you don't
know because the intention to hurt
intention to engage your sensuality
intention to harm intention to be cruel
is always unit
saluted every single time in every
single being regardless of the culture
mental faculties it's always rooted in
them resisting that whatever they
feeling at the time it cannot that's why
it's unwholesome inherently like you
cannot be cruel for the good reason
impossible impossible because
intentional cruelty requires as its
necessary basis you resisting high
feeling so the person who has developed
that much instead of his mind that much
that practice of peacefulness regardless
of what he felt in non craving there
it's an automatic contentment yet
contentment is there yeah automatically
yeah it's a result of it he needs to
also discern that yeah he would if he
already developed at that point he
really said that he's content amidst
this contenting environment and that's
that's how moody to describe him
angry to nicaya how does he get rid of
discontent but practicing mudita yeah
which is a contact me see it's another
step further of the same principle that
you started with in regard to Metta he's
just it's even less personal so now it's
not even any more about others and your
involvement with others so this so that
it's really on the level of content
discontent being able to endure
discontent being able to endure elements
being able to know sickness being able
to endure abuse disagreement criticism
being able to do basically anything that
you're subjected to and not lose the
mind of contentment
that's mudita and you see that's already
higher than just enduring on your will
yeah it said that spiritual joy so to
speak with people like I don't know it
use it yeah yeah cuz spiritual joy tends
to be like it's a joy that's not
connected with whatever's happened
exactly yeah it's it's truly
imperturbable by any circumstances it's
like like same same joy in jhana yeah
Jody you secluded and unaffected free of
concern in regard to the entire it was a
strengthening of what you're doing yeah
we can only strengthen and then you
could see come naturally if you will
develop that principle further it's the
after equanimity completely and you
would like have to sort of you know the
patchwork anti loose ends to connect
your love of love of meta meta loving
with utter indifference towards
everything everyone including your own
life your own emotions your own state of
being which our hunt would be developing
but if what we describe you realize how
meta would lead to Karuna which leads to
basically contentment amidst this
content look your mind does not resist
unpleasant circumstances unpleasant
elements and what is that result what
does a culminating in after equanimity
in regard to good or bad so yes by all
means practice Bronwyn ours correctly
yeah and another description of mudita
just get that rule that is good when you
can again where the Buddha talks about
the three assemblies the it was the
foremost assembly be divided assembly
and the harmonious assembly harmonious
assembly was monks who live regarding
each other with eyes of affection not
quarreling no disputes with non conflict
yeah that is how they they live in the
divine abiding of mudita so this monks
living together with others so what's
the best way to regard somebody with a
friendly eye to keep visualizing and
reminding us all what a good friend that
person is that depends on the
circumstances because if on another
occasion they don't do something you
deem is a good friend we do means your
whole friendship then is affected by it
means your whole state of mind would be
affected by it but if on the other hand
you only care about your own state of
mind of friendliness regardless of who
you live with
who comes your way you protect your mind
you will protect child you will be
automatically inadvertently incapable of
ill-will towards them so which is better
circumstantially not being affected by
your will or becoming unable to be
affected by your will the answers
obvious so the best way to regard
yourself with affection and regard
others that you live with with a friend
in the affection in ours is basically
protect your own mind from your will
from resistance in regard to how you
feel can you have any will towards a
person that said something disagreeable
to you if you don't mind experiencing
this agreeable feeling it's
inconceivable to hate that person no
matter what they do and you would not
need to deal with anything either in
order to maintain that because the
framework remained unaffected you don't
have to look at the politics don't need
to manage them in order for you to not
hate that it simply by not resisting the
disagreeable feeling that you're
experiencing you cannot hate whoever was
perceived to be the cause of that
disagreeable feeling that's already
matter done properly so you're not you
know you're covering all circumstances
it might arise you're basically finding
like like a gateway to which
circumstances have to arise and instead
of chasing and managing and dealing with
preventing circumstances you realize all
I need to do is protect the Gateway and
not lose the sight of it then whatever
then I know it's in whatever is out and
when it's out and that's all you need to
know that's how you protect it find in
the context that is universal to good or
bad agreeable or disagreeable content or
discontent and then protect that context
and that's how you go beyond content and
discontent
and that context is not resisting what
you're currently feeling and you always
have to be feeling something peace of
peacefulness well know you will
peacefulness will come as a result of it
as a combination of your absence of your
resistance towards what you feel
that's the peace peace is not not
feeling the pain peace is not being
disturbed by the pain or not being
pulled by the pleasure there are non
conflict not the conflict internally
exactly then that's another thing can
you have conflict with anybody outside
without you already being conflicted
with what you're feeling at the time do
you refusing to accept impossible so if
you remove the conflict you can spend a
whole life technical whole life in
trying to eradicate the conflict out
there in the world and you will fail
because that's not where the conflict is
rooted it's rooted in in basically how
you parallel every single individual is
feeling at a time they are resisting it
or giving in to it that's already the
root of the conflict so you remove that
internal conflict it would be impossible
to be conflicted even if the whole world
is seeking conflict with you to the
point of hurt physically harming you